Rafael Garcia

rafagarfer@gmail.com London, UK

Profile

Software Engineer, holder of Bachelor and Master's degree in Computer Engineering at the University of Granada, Spain. Building Android apps in the UK market since 2014, with a more recent interest in mobile cross-platform solutions. I consider myself honest, pragmatic, driven and curious, always looking for new ways to solve problems, improve teams and mentor colleagues.

Work Experience

• Memrise (London, UK)

Lead Android Developer | August 2021 - Present Senior Android Developer | October 2018 - July 2021

Implementation of features across different squads in the company: engagement, language learning, core and consumer experience. Promoter of good practises inside the team, with special drive for architecture (MVI), testing and multi-platform solutions (Kotlin Multiplatform). More recently leading the team and working closely to product and company stakeholders.

Developit 4U (Remote, side projects)

Founder and Developer | June 2018 - June 2020

Small company created together with two colleagues. We tackled university ad-hoc projects on the mobile health ecosystem involving wearable devices and health monitoring. My responsibilities went from meeting clients and scoping their requirements, to building the end to end solutions, both from a mobile point of view (Android) and backend perspective (Ktor).

Sportlobster (London, UK)

Lead Android Developer | January 2017 - March 2018 Android Developer | October 2015 - December 2016

Transformed a very outdated sport social media app into one that followed the latest standards in Android development like MVP, Material Design guidelines and unit/UI testing. Worked very closely with the design, API and QA teams. Responsible for mentoring team members and recruiting new ones.

Rippll Ltd (London, UK)

Junior Android Developer | June 2014 - October 2015

Android and iOS developer with main focus on Android. Responsible for commercial bespoke apps, internal products and R&D. Development and maintenance of Geowave SDK, a behavioural location engine that knows where consumers interact with apps most often.

Education & Qualifications

Bachelor and Master's Degree in Computer Engineering (University of Granada)

- Dissertation: "mHealthDroid. Design, implementation and validation of a mobile framework for agile development of mHealth applications for Android". Awarded with distinction followed by two articles published in scientific journals.
- Erasmus student at Warsaw University of Technology (Poland) for one year.
- Award Emilio Herrera Linares at the University of Granada for the best CS dissertation.

Language Skills

Spanish is my mother tongue. I speak **English** fluently with a *beautiful* and *subtle* (disclaimer: *some people may disagree...*) Spanish accent. I also speak **Polish** like a 4 years old.

Programming languages and Skills

Programming languages: Kotlin and Java mainly. Used others like Typescript, Objective C or C++.

Skills:

- Love discussing about mobile architecture as I think it is key for healthy apps.
- Very intrigued by native Multiplatform solutions like Kotlin Multiplatform.
- Unit testing advocate.
- Interested in a wide-range of engineering topics such as design patterns, functional programming or design systems.
- While still an amateur, I have some experience building APIs and backends using Ktor.
- Pragmatic and flexible developer, I believe the answer to most questions starts with "well, it depends".
- Good communicator with non-technical stakeholders.

Projects

- I write tech articles on my site <u>rafagarcia.dev</u>, where you can also find my <u>portfolio</u>.
- I share code for all my pet projects on my GitHub account: Rafagf.
- <u>mHealthDroid</u>: open-source framework designed to facilitate rapid and easy development of health applications for Android. It has 200+ stars and 100+ forks.

Hobbies and interests

- **Travelling:** getting lost far from home and meeting people from different cultures is probably one of the things I enjoy the most. In 2018, my girlfriend and I left everything behind to travel Asia for 7 months.
- Animals: animal's lover. Whilst living in Spain, I was part of a non-profit organisation called "Animals without luck", where I provided temporarily shelter for stray dogs. Now I give permanent shelter to my rescue dog Nala!
- Sports: very passionate about sports, specially tennis and football. Big fan of Rafa Nadal!
- **Failed blogger**: I have owned and abandoned blogs about different topics, the most recent one about travelling called <u>itfeelsgoodtobelost.com</u>.